(
"ai_sub_version": "1.9.2",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 2,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": false,
"scrub": true
)
思い通りにいかないことだらけ
Everything's just not going the way I want
どうしようもなく自己嫌悪
I'm feeling so much self-hatred, there's nothing I can do
八百万の痛みや悲しみから
From the myriad of pains and sorrows
逃げ込める場所を探してる
I'm searching for a place to flee into
いっそ岩の隙間に引きこもって
I'll go and hide in a crevice between the rocks
月も太陽も無視して寝よう
Ignoring both the moon and the sun, I'll sleep
生まれてきたことの意味なんて
The meaning of having been born and all that
知らない、分かんないよ
I don't know, I don't understand!
でも そんな風に思えるってこと
But the fact that you can feel that way
それは
That's
君がもっともっと素敵になれる力があるって
It shows you have the power to become even more wonderful
教えてるんだよ
It's telling you that
さあ 神のまにまに 仰せのままに
Now, as the gods will, as they command
誰だって地球を愛してる
Everyone loves the earth
飲めや歌えや どんちゃん騒ぎ
Drink and sing, make a huge racket
たまにゃそんなんもいいんじゃね？
Isn't that fine every once in a while?
そうさ北も南も 右も左も
That's right, north or south, right or left
なんだかんだ地球を愛してる
One way or another, we love the earth
泥んこだけど 歩いて行ける
It's muddy, but we can walk on
まだまだ先は長いさ
The road ahead is still long
ただ 正しい人でいたいだけ
I just want to be a righteous person
きっと誰もがそう願っているけど
Surely everyone wishes for that, but
八百万の心の醜さに
By the ugliness of myriad hearts
苦しめられる毎日さ
I'm tormented every day
僕が生まれてきたこと 奇跡と言えば
If I say that my being born was a miracle
聞こえはいいけど
It sounds nice, but
それは単なる偶然にすぎなくて
That's nothing more than a mere coincidence
やっぱり意味なんてないさ
After all, there's no meaning in it
でも 例えば君に
But, for example, for you...
腕を振る
Waving my arms
やっと出会えたんだ
We finally met
それは君がとっても素敵な人だって
Because it's telling me that you're a wonderful person
教えてるんだよ
I'm telling you
そうさ 神のまにまに
That's right, at the god's will
仰せのままに
Just as they command
誰だって地球を愛してる
Everyone loves the Earth
僕が笑って
If I laugh
君も笑えば
And you laugh too
許せないことなんてないよ
There's nothing that can't be forgiven
そうさ 男も女も
That's right, both men and women
恋しかるべき
Should fall in love
そんなふうに地球は回ってる
That's how the Earth turns
泥んこだけど歩いて行こう
Though it's muddy, let's keep walking
まだまだ先は長いさ
The road ahead is still long
本当に大事なものなんて
Truly important things
案外くだらないことの中にあるよ
Are often found within trivial matters
時にはみんなでバカ騒ぎ
Sometimes let's all go wild
裸踊りで
Dancing naked
おお笑い
Laughing out loud
そうさ 神のまにまに
That's right, at the god's will
仰せのままに
Just as they command
もっともっと自分を愛せるよ
You can love yourself more and more
鏡を見てごらんよ
Look in the mirror
もうわかるでしょ
You already know, right?
みんなを照らす光さ
You are the light that shines on everyone
そうさ 神のまにまに
That's right, at the god's will
みんなありがとう
Thank you everyone
やっぱり地球を愛してる
After all, I love the Earth
花を咲かそう
Let's make flowers bloom
大きな花を
Large flowers
天まで届くくらいの
Ones that reach up to the sky
ラララ...
La la la...
はーい！
Hi!
始まりましたー！
We've started!
イエーイ！
Yay!
おめでとうー！
Congratulations!
ありがとうー！
Thank you!
ありがとー！
今日はね、こんなに素敵な大切な仲間の皆が、
Today, so many wonderful and precious friends
お祝いに駆けつけてくれて、
have rushed here to celebrate with me,
本当に本当に嬉しく思っています。
and I am truly, truly happy.
皆ありがとねー！
Thank you everyone!
ありがとうございまーす！
Thank you very much!
見に来てくれてる皆もありがとー！
Thanks to everyone who's watching too!
ありがとうございまーす！
Thank you very much!
というわけで、早速皆を
So, I'd like to introduce
紹介したいとおもいますよ！
everyone right away!
お、シロちゃんから自己紹介お願いします！
Oh, Siro-chan, please introduce yourself!
よろしいんですか？
Is it okay?
はーい！イニシエからのそらとも、
Hi! An old-timer Soratomo,
電脳少女シロだよ！
I'm Dennou Shoujo Siro!
今日はそらちゃんが今まで頑張った
Today is the day that Sora-chan's
集大成の日ということで、
hard work has finally culminated,
駆けつけました。
so I rushed here.
皆で盛り上げて応援していくぜー！
Let's all get excited and cheer her on!
イエーイ！
Yay!
そして！
And!
はい！
Yes!
起立、気をつけ、こんにちは！
Stand up, attention, hello!
イニシエというにはちょっと
I feel a bit like a newcomer
若輩者な気もしますが、
compared to the "old-timers,"
月ノ美兎と申します。
but my name is Tsukino Mito.
よろしくお願いいたします。
Nice to meet you.
美兎様100万人おめでとう！
Mito-sama, congrats on 1 million!
おめでとうー！
Congratulations!
そらちゃん本当に100万人おめでとう！
Sora-chan, truly, congrats on 1 million!
そこにいる皆とそらちゃんに向かって。
To everyone there and to Sora-chan.
皆さーん、富士葵です、
Everyone, I'm Fuji Aoi,
お願いします！
please take care of me!
おめでとうー！
Congratulations!
えー、イニシエのそらとも、
Um, an old-timer Soratomo,
起立気をつけ、え、おはよ！
stand up, attention, uh, morning!
マブダチ、由似です。
Bestie, I'm Yuni.
よろしくお願いします！
Nice to meet you!
あれ、美兎ちゃん？
Wait, Mito-chan?
あれ、由似ちゃんってもしかして...
Wait, Yuni-chan, are you...
私、こういう場では後輩に
I've often been the junior
なることが多かったんですけど、
in situations like this,
今回いますね、
but this time I see
私よりも後輩が。
there's a junior to me.
ちょっと、一学年下では
Wait, I might be one
あるかもしれませんけども...
school year below you, but...
何か、何で急に、ねえ、
Why did you suddenly, you know,
出してきた、そういうこと。
bring that up?
ギスギスやる？
Are we doing the "awkward friction" bit?
100万人配信でギスギスやりますか？
Doing awkward friction on the 1 million stream?
仲良くなれて。でも、こうやって言いつつも私たちはもう、かなりもう長くやっている方で。
We've become close. But despite that, we've actually been doing this for a long time.
そうだね。/ そうそう。
That's true. / Right.
このメンバーで集まるのすら久しぶり。
It's been a while since this group even gathered together.
いや、本当だよね。/ そうですね。
Yeah, it really has. / That's right.
2年ぶりくらい？
Is it about two years?
ちょっとこの中で1年以内に会った人いないですよ。
Wait, I haven't met anyone in this group within the last year.
いやーいないかも。/ 会ってない。
Yeah, maybe not. / Haven't met.
あ、そらちゃんは、AZKiちゃんと...
Well, I met AZKi-chan...
そらさんの前ですよ。
That was in your presence, Sora-san.
私は、皆と1年以内に会って... あ、会ってない、会ってない。
I haven't met everyone within a year... wait, no I haven't, I haven't.
あ、会ってるか。ロボ子さんとAZKiちゃん...
Oh, wait. Roboco-san and AZKi-chan...
AZKiちゃんだけだよ。
It's just AZKi-chan.
あれ、AZKiちゃんだけ？
Oh, just AZKi-chan?
仲悪そう。
Sounds like we don't get along.
今日で仲を深めていきましょう。
Let's deepen our bond today.
というわけで、今日のハッシュタグなんですけど...
So, about today's hashtag...
「#ときのそら100万人への軌跡」というハッシュタグになっておりますので...
The hashtag is "#ThePathTo1MillionSubscribersForTokinoSora."
ぜひぜひ皆さん、つぶやいて...
Please, everyone, tweet about it...
最近赤ちゃん化してると言われてるけど、赤ちゃんではないです。
People say I've been acting like a baby lately, but I'm not a baby.
そこでね、AZKiちゃんとみこちゃんが仲良くなれるのかな、とか。
So, maybe AZKi-chan and Miko-chan can get closer, or something.
そういうのをどしどしツイートしてもらえたら...
If you could tweet things like that...
私たちとっても嬉しいと思うので、よろしくお願いします。
We'd be very happy, so please do.
よろしくお願いしまーす！
Please look forward to it!
はい。というわけで、今日は最初歌だったんですけど...
Yes. So, we started with songs today...
歌以外にも実はいろいろありまして。
But there's actually more than just songs.
この5年間、50年でもあったので...
These 5 years felt like 50 years, so...
年表というのを、私ちょっと作ってみまして。
I've put together a timeline.
そう。で、皆と同じイベントとかライブもあるので...
Right. And since there are events and lives we shared...
その話とかをしていけたらいいなと思っております。
I'd like to talk about those.
楽しみ。
Looking forward to it.
そらちゃんの配信で振り返らさせてもらうわ。
I'll reflect on them during Sora-chan's stream.
そうそう。ついでに。
Yeah, while you're at it.
はい。で、前半は、ロボ子さんとAZKiちゃんに。
Okay. So, for the first half, Roboco-san and AZKi-chan...
そして後半は、みこちゃんとすいちゃん。
And for the second half, Miko-chan and Sui-chan.
ちょっとね、順番は色々あって...
The order is a bit mixed up...
AZKiちゃんとみこちゃんが一緒じゃないんかーとか思うかもしれないけど。
You might wonder why AZKi and Miko aren't together...
でもでも、後でまた5人集まるところもあるかもしれないので。
But we might all gather together again later.
よろしくお願いします。
So please stay tuned.
というわけで、早速年表に行っちゃいましょう！
With that said, let's dive into the timeline!
いえーい！
Yay!
というわけで、ときのそら年表。前半はこのお二人に来てもらっています！
And so, the Tokino Sora timeline. These two are joining me for the first half!
お願いしまーす。
Please join us.
あれ？なんか雰囲気がちょっと。
Wait, the atmosphere is a bit...
こんにちは、わたくしロボ子です。そして...
Hello, I am Roboco. And...
AZ... AZKiです。
A... AZKi here.
よろしくお願いいたします。
Nice to meet you.
なんかすごい、こんなにお淑やかだったかな、さっきまで。
Wow, were you guys this refined just a moment ago?
情報番組さながら。
Like a news program.
ロボ子さん、いらっしゃいって聞いてきたんですけど。
I heard Roboco-san was coming.
違うんですよ。
No, that's not it.
一緒に年表を見ていきたいなと思っております。
I want to look through the timeline with you.
気になりますね。
I'm curious.
前半はね、そう、私がデビューした2017年の9月から2019年までとなっております。
The first half covers from September 2017, when I debuted, to 2019.
2017年！
2017!
当時のVTuberっていうと、全然もうこのメンバーと...
VTubers back then... it was just this group and...
今日ね、他に来てくれる後半組の子と、そんなにいっぱい、いなかった。
...the group coming in the second half. There weren't that many of us.
だってさ、30人以内だったよね、絶対。
Right, there were definitely fewer than 30.
そうそうそう。
Yeah, exactly.
今こそホロライブさんが「箱」って呼ばれているように...
Now that Hololive is called a "group"...
VTuber皆がちょっと「箱」みたいな雰囲気があって。
...all VTubers have that kind of "group" feel.
ねえ、そうだよね。
Yeah, that's true.
ちょっとね、そんな私たちそれぞれ後輩ももう、できる立ち位置になっちゃって。
And now we're all in positions where we have juniors.
みんな「箱」持ちというか。
Everyone's part of a group now.
時代は四大巨頭...
The era of the four giants...
いやいやいや、間に挟まれロボ子です。ありがとうございます。
No, no, no. I'm Roboco, caught in the middle. Thank you.
今回見るのは、まだVTuberというのが知られて間もない時期の年表ということになっております。
What we're looking at now is a timeline from when VTubers were barely known.
私がインターネットカチカチオタクだった時の。
Back when I was a clicking internet otaku.
みんなのを見てたっていう。
Watching everyone else.
楽しみ。
Exciting.
ねえ、その時のやつを是非ね、見ていけたらいいなと思っております。
Yeah, I'd really love to look back at those times.
それでは早速、年表見ていきましょう。まずは、こちらです！
So without further ado, let's look at the timeline. First is this!
こちら、私の1年目となっておりまして。
This is my first year.
おー！
Oh!
これは、隠してあるんですか？
Is this hidden?
そうなんです。一緒に話せそうだなって思う場所とか...
That's right. Parts that I think we can talk about together...
私がなんか色々変わったなって思うポイントとか。
and points where I feel like a lot has changed.
うーん、なんかちょっと...
Hmm, somehow...
こういう風に、ちょっと赤くしてありますので。
I've made it a bit like this... in red.
あー、なるほど。え、すでに見えてるところだけでお腹いっぱいというか...
Ah, I see. Even just looking at what's already visible is quite a lot...
全部話せるとは思うんだけど...
I think we can talk about everything, but...
まあまあまあ、まずはね、1個目から見ていきたいと思います。
Well, well, well, let's look at the first one first.
えー、1個目。あれかな？お、それからですね。やっぱり、1個目だからね。
The first one... is it that one? Since it's from the start, after all.
うん。1枚目は、こちらです。
Yes. The first one is this one.
ああー！そらだ、やっぱり！
Ah! It's 'Sora-dai', as I thought!
そう、バーチャルJKとしてね、ときのそら初ニコニコ生放送だったんですよね。
So, as a 'Virtual JK', it was Tokino Sora's first Nico Nico Live broadcast.
あ、初めてはYouTubeじゃなくて、ニコニコ。
Oh, the first time wasn't YouTube, but Nico Nico.
そう、最初の数ヶ月はニコニコ生放送だったので、YouTubeに来たのは結構遅いんですよね。
Yes, for the first few months it was on Nico Nico Live, so coming to YouTube was actually quite late.
もちろん存じております。ありがとうございます！もちろんね！
Of course I know that. Thank you! Of course!
実は、こちら。その一番最初の映像がね、なんと用意されているということなので。
Actually, we have the very first video prepared here, so...
ちょっと見てみましょう。どうぞ！
...let's take a look. Here you go!
見えてますか？映ってますか？（シロ：かわいい！）
Can you see me? Is it on? (Siro: Cute!)
お、声届いてますかね？（シロ：かわいい！）
Oh, is my voice reaching you? (Siro: Cute!)
いやでもこれさ、BGMもないって、本当に寂しい...
But you know, having no BGM is really lonely...
確かにないんだ。え、ちょっと大丈夫そう？
Indeed, there isn't any. Wait, is this okay?
ね。まあまだJKだからさ、あんときは。あ、見てみましょう。
Yeah. Well, I was still a JK back then. Let's see.
みなさんこんばんは！
Good evening, everyone!
そして初めまして！ときのそらです。（そら：頑張って元気出そうとしてる...）
And nice to meet you! I'm Tokino Sora. (Sora: I'm trying so hard to be energetic...)
2000年生まれの17歳、高校2年生です。（シロ：すごいストーリー...）
I'm 17 years old, born in 2000, a high school junior. (Siro: What a story...)
あ、本当に初めての配信なので、ふわーっと、ちょっと気合が入ってます。
Actually, since it's my first broadcast, I'm a bit fired up!
あ、髪型とかね、変わった...（シロ・あおい：透明感！かわいい！）
Ah, the hairstyle and such have changed... (Siro/Aoi: So clear! Cute!)
え、なんか本当に、なんか垢抜けてない感があるというか...
Somehow, she looks really... unrefined? Or rather...
ちょっとおぼこい感じ。
She has an 'innocent' feel.
おぼこい？なんですの、その日本語。
Innocent? What's with that word?
なに？おぼこい？
What? Innocent?
つまり今は色気付いたって言いたいんですか？（シロ：成長したんだな...）
In other words, you want to say she's become more mature now, right? (Siro: You've grown up...)
そしてそして、2017年はね、ハロウィンがあったりあん肝が出てきたり...
And in 2017, there was Halloween and Ankimo appeared...
まあそのあとね、次のパネルがあるから見てみましょう。
Well, after that, there's the next panel, so let's see.
こちらです。
This is it.
あ、実はね、クリスマスが初めてのYouTubeなんですよ。
Actually, Christmas was the first YouTube broadcast.
だいぶ長いことニコニコだったんですね。
Wow, you were on Nico Nico for quite a long time.
そう、お二人は、初めてのYouTubeをやった時... 生放送をやった時ってどんな感じだった？
Yes, so... when you two did your first YouTube Live broadcasts, how was it?
まあ私は結構早いですよ。もうその次からYouTubeだったと思います。
Well, I was quite early. I think I moved to YouTube right after.
そっかそっか。2017年の末というか... そうですね、凛先輩とかに教えてもらってやったって感じ。
I see, I see. It was like the end of 2017... Yes, Rin-senpai and others taught me how to do it.
ほうら！誰も知らなくて、裏方の方がYouTubeの...
See! No one knew about it, except the staff...
そうそう、JK組でね。そうそう、私も知らなかった。
Yeah, we were the 'JK group' back then. I didn't know either.
なるほど。シロはさっき裏でそらちゃんと喋ったんですけど...
I see. Siro, I was talking with Sora-chan earlier...
初配信をファンの方を電脳世界に誘う、そんなイメージある。（そら：そうそう）
In the first broadcast, inviting fans to the 'electronic world'... (Sora: Yes, that's the image.)
嬉しい！やって、ファンの方だけ巨大化したり、天井から吊られちゃったりする魔法を...
I'm glad! I used magic that made only the fans grow huge, or get hung from the ceiling...
シロ喋りながら、ファンがどんどん巨大化していきました。ファンがフックに吊るされてDead by Daylightの世界で...
While Siro was talking, the fans kept getting bigger, or got caught on hooks like in Dead by Daylight...
殺人鬼の気持ちで...（そら：それはそれでいいな）いつ捕まるんだろって、生きた心地がしなかった！
I felt like a killer... (Sora: That's fine in its own way.) I was wondering when I'd get caught, I didn't feel alive!
いやでも、それぞれもやっぱり初めての生放送、こう聞くと全然違う感じだね。（あおい：歴史ありですね）
Well, hearing each person's first live broadcast, they're all so different. (Aoi: There's history here.)
そしてそして、次がパネルになってますが、次はこちらです。
And next is the panel... here it is.
お！
Oh!
はい、ということでここでね、チャンネル登録者数が10万人ということでなっております。（シロ・あおい：すごい！）
So, here, the channel subscribers reached 100,000. (Siro/Aoi: Amazing!)
結構早いのかなーって私は思った。
I thought that was pretty fast.
確かに。え、だって活動始めた時、この時期に10万人って思ってないですよね？
Indeed. I mean, when we started, did we think we'd reach 100,000 by then?
思ってない。1万もいくかなーくらいの感覚。（シロ：めっちゃわかる！）
No. I was more like, 'I wonder if we'll even reach 10,000?' (Siro: I totally get that!)
そしてこのあとは、いろんなところでコラボとかいろんな人と会うようになってきてて、あおいちゃんと初めてコラボしたりとか、あとはね、キズナアイちゃんの誕生日イベントに。
And after this, I started collaborating and meeting various people in different places... like my first collab with Aoi-chan, or Kizuna AI-chan's birthday event.
覚えてる！お二人はね、出てらっしゃいましたもんね。
I remember! You two were there too.
心のなかにいたよ！（シロ：見てましたからね！）
We were there in spirit! (Siro: I was watching!)
でも、いないのが意外なくらい、もう出てきたときからすごかった。
It was surprising we weren't there... no, from the moment you appeared, it was amazing.
すごい感動的でしたよ、見てる方からしたら。（シロ：アイちゃんのカチューシャとか...）
It was really moving to watch. (Siro: Like Ai-chan's headband...)
みんな人間のシルエットがぴょこぴょこ付いて、なんかみんなアイちゃーん！ってなって。（シロ・あおい：巨大化！すごい！）
...everyone was wearing those human silhouettes and bouncing around, and everyone was like 'Ai-chaaan!' (Siro/Aoi: It was huge! Amazing!)
というわけでね、2年目に行く前に...
So, before we move on to the second year...
今回その年ごとにメッセージをいただいておりまして。
...we've received messages for each of those years.
1年目は、2017年、最初に見えてますか？ってさっき出てた、1年目のスタイリスト、2017年のスタイリストをやってくださった稲垣先生からのメッセージが届いておりますので、読みたいと思います。
For the first year, 2017, we have a message from Inagaki-sensei, who was the stylist for the 'can you see me?' look we saw earlier. I'll read it now.
お願いします！
Please do!
ときのそらさんへ、
Dear Toki no Sora-san,
初期のそらのデザインとモデリングをさせていただきました、いかきです。
I am Ikaki, the one who handled your initial design and modeling.
このたびは、YouTube登録者数100万人、たいへんおめでとうございます！
Congratulations on reaching 1 million YouTube subscribers!
これまでの軌跡を追っていらっしゃるとお伺いして、
Hearing that you're tracing back your journey so far,
拙いながらも筆を取らせていただきました。
I've taken up my pen, humble as I am.
せっかくですので、すこし思い出話をしようかと思います。
Since I have the chance, I'd like to share a few memories.
ふと記憶を思い返してみると、
Looking back,
あれからもうすぐ6年が経つようです。
it seems nearly 6 years have passed since then.
最近では、日々大きくなっていくそらちゃんとホロライブの羽ばたきが目に沁みます。
Lately, seeing you and Hololive growing and taking flight day by day truly moves me.
活動を始めてからの年を数えるにも、もうすぐ片手では足りなくなってしまうんですね。
Soon, I won't even be able to count the years since you started on one hand.
感慨深いです。
It's deeply moving.
実は初めて名前を知ったのは、
Actually, the first time I learned your name was...
デビュー直前にふとTwitterで目にした告知ツイートでした。
...from an announcement tweet I happened to see on Twitter just before your debut.
その時の私は嬉しい気持ちと、驚きが混じった心情でした。
At that moment, my heart was a mix of joy and surprise.
今ではホロライブのアイドルとして、走り続けて止まらないそらちゃんですが、
While you're now a Hololive idol who never stops running forward,
デザイン当時は名前すらなく、「バーチャルJK」というキーワードがあるだけでした。
back when you were being designed, you didn't even have a name—only the keyword "Virtual JK".
デザインから3Dモデルの完成まで1ヶ月弱という期間でしたが、
The period from design to the completion of the 3D model was less than a month,
私の中には「爽やかな学園アニメのような」
but in my mind, keywords like "like a refreshing school anime,"
「清楚で穏やかな」
"neat and calm,"
「よく晴れた早朝の空」というキーワードが固まっていました。
and "a clear early morning sky" had already taken shape.
どうでしょう、今のそらちゃんにもピッタリだと思いませんか？
What do you think? Don't you think they suit the current Sora-chan perfectly?
これらのキーワードに合わせてデザインしていたので、
Since I designed you with those keywords in mind,
「デザインから読み取っていただけたのかな…？」と思えるほどぴったりの印象だったんです。
it felt so fitting that I wondered if you'd read them right off the design.
天才ですね(笑)
I guess I'm a genius (laughs).
さて、配信活動が始まってからしばらく経ったあとの話。
Now, about some time after your streaming activities began.
一時期、私には自信をなくしていた頃がありました。
There was a period when I had lost my confidence.
先ほどお話しした初期の衣装デザインには、もう1つだけ盛り込んだキーワードがあります。
In the initial costume design I mentioned earlier, there was actually one more keyword I included.
それは…「無個性で、未完成な」。
That was... "plain and incomplete."
今のそらちゃんからは思いつかないイメージですね。
An image unimaginable for the current Sora-chan.
当初、地味で華やかさの少ないデザインだったかと思います。
In the beginning, I think the design was quite sober and lacked flashiness.
当時の私はそらちゃんの個性を演出したい！という未来にかける希望よりも、
At the time, rather than the hope for the future of wanting to showcase your individuality,
持たせたい印象を優先してしまったのです。
I prioritized the impression I wanted to convey.
少し視点は違うかもしれませんが、
Though the perspective might be slightly different,
ご自分を「水」と例えていたそらちゃんの苦悩は自分に通じるところがありました。
Sora-chan's struggles—when you compared yourself to "water"—resonated with me.
ふと目に入ってしまった心無いコメントで傷ついたことがあれば、
Whether it was being hurt by heartless comments that caught my eye,
完璧なモデルに仕上げることができなかったことも。
or the fact that I couldn't finish the model to perfection.
周りを見れば素敵なクリエイターさんばかりで、劣等感に苛まれる日々です。
Looking around, there were only wonderful creators, and I spent my days plagued by a sense of inferiority.
考えれば考えるほどに、「こうなるなら自分が担当させていただくべきではなかった」という気持ちすらありました。
The more I thought about it, the more I felt that I shouldn't have been the one in charge.
しかし、結局そんな苦悩からもそらちゃんやそらともさんに救われました。
However, in the end, I was saved from those struggles by you and the Soratomo.
思い返してみればどうでしょう、
Looking back,
いつだって前に進もうと挫けず立ち向かう一生懸命さと強さ、
your earnestness and strength to always try to move forward without breaking,
透き通った心地良い歌声にも、何度も勇気をいただきました。
and your clear, pleasant singing voice, have given me courage many times.
立派な個性で堂々と活動しているそらちゃんはいつだって眩しいです。
Sora-chan, actively performing with such a magnificent personality, is always dazzling.
それを見守るそらともさんも皆様暖かく、ありのままを喜んで楽しんでいらっしゃって…
The Soratomo watching over you are all so warm, rejoicing and enjoying things just as they are...
3周年ライブのときにふと、ずっと引きずっていた自分が急に恥ずかしくなったんです。
During the 3rd anniversary live, I suddenly felt ashamed of the self I had been dragging along.
…目の前で輝く歌姫にサイリウムを振って応援しては感動し、
Watching the shining diva before my eyes, waving a penlight and being moved by her...
日々の配信では、画面の前で同じゲームで遊んでは笑って、
Laughing together in front of the screen while playing the same games during daily streams...
新しい衣装や誕生日、記念日には自分のことのように喜んではイラストを描いたり、
Rejoicing over new outfits, birthdays, and anniversaries as if they were my own, drawing illustrations,
新曲の動画の公開を心待ちにしたり、
and eagerly awaiting the release of new song videos...
ファン作品を観て、聴いて、感激したり、
Watching and listening to fan works and being deeply moved,
時には不器用にそらともさんとコミュニケーションをしてみたり…
or sometimes awkwardly communicating with other Soratomo...
語りきれないですが、たくさんの思い出はどれも本当に楽しい時間でした。
I can't list them all, but every one of those many memories was a truly wonderful time.
きっとほかのそらともさんも、それぞれに素敵な思い出があることかと思います。
I'm sure every other Soratomo has their own wonderful memories as well.
どれもすべて、そらさんから生まれたんです。
All of them were born from you, Sora-san.
あなたの熱量に集まった、たくさんの「想い出」。
The many "memories" gathered by your passion.
それがあるからこそ、0から歩みを進めてきたあなたが、
Because they exist, I am certain that's why you, who have walked from zero,
「今」という大舞台にたどり着くことができた理由なんだなと、私は確信しています。
were able to reach the grand stage of "now."
本当に素敵な旅路が残っていますよ。
A truly wonderful journey still lies ahead.
いまこの時をご一緒できて心から嬉しいです。
I am heartfully happy to be with you at this moment.
改めて、100万人おめでとうございます。
Once again, congratulations on 1 million subscribers.
山盛りいっぱいの感謝を。いかき。
With heaps of gratitude, Ikaki.
はい、どうですかそらちゃん。
Yes, how do you feel, Sora-chan?
いや...
No...
泣いちゃうよ。そらともさんしかいないんだから。
You're gonna cry. It's only Soratomos here, after all.
いや、こんなになんか、たくさんのメッセージいただけると、思ってなかったですし、
No, I didn't think I would receive so many messages, and...
なんか、あ、こんな風に応援してくださってるんだなっていうのを初めて見たので、なんか、ちょっと...
...it's like, I'm seeing for the first time how much I'm being supported, so, it's a bit...
そらちゃんの目から美しい水が流れているんですが。
Beautiful water is flowing from Sora-chan's eyes.
すごい、本当になんか、すごいそらちゃんと違った視点でそらちゃんの歩みを体験されてて、またそらともさんともちょっと違った視点も持ってらっしゃいましたね。
It's amazing, they're experiencing Sora-chan's journey from a different perspective than hers, and they had a slightly different perspective from the Soratomos too.
そうですね、なんかすごい、そっちにも物語があるっていう。感激しましたね。
Yeah, it's like there's a story there too. I was moved.
感激しましたね。
I was moved too.
いや、なんか、いや、こちらの方こそなんかなんて言うんだろう、
No, I mean, on my end, how should I put it...
確かに私は今もですけど、そこまで強い個性はないとは思ってるんですけど、
Certainly, even now, I don't think I have that strong of a personality...
でも、その私が一番私らしいと思っていたし、
...but that version of me felt the most like me,
最初の私を、見た瞬間から、私は私だし、
and from the moment I saw my first self, I was me...
本当に、あ、私として生まれてきて、17年間よかったなと思ってるので、
I really think it's been a good 17 years being born as me,
17歳になってデビューできたのは本当に私にとっての宝物なので、
so being able to debut at 17 is truly a treasure for me.
こんな風に言って頂けるのは、本当にありがたいです。ありがとうございます。
I'm really grateful to be told these things. Thank you.
いやー、よかった。
Wow, that was good.
よかった。
It was good.
ねー。とね、そんな感じで。
Yeah. And so...
はい。以上、1年目でした！
Yes. That was the 1st year!
濃いなー。
That was dense.
いや、1年目だけでだいぶ濃いですね。
Yeah, it's quite dense just for the 1st year.
そうですね。
True.
さあ、そんな中でこういろいろね、VTuberが世界に、世界というかみんなに知ってもらえるようになって、
Now, amidst all that, as VTubers started to become known to the world—or rather, to everyone—
2年目が始まるというわけですが、そちら2年目の年表行ってみましょう！こちらです！
the 2nd year began. Let's check out the 2nd year timeline! Here it is!
はい、というわけでね、こちらの2年目のパネルはちょっと長いんですけども、
Yes, and so, the 2nd year panel is a bit long,
めくりが多いですね。
lots of things to flip.
そうですね。まあそこは一気にめくっちゃおうと思います！
Right. Well, I'm going to flip them all at once!
おお、めくっちゃよ！いけー！
Oh, flipping them! Go!
こちらです！
Here it is!
はい。ここはいベントとかアニメがいっぱいあった時期。
Yes. This was a time with lots of events and anime.
ニコニコ超パーティー2018、バーチャル大晦日、アニメ「バーチャルさんはみている」の時期ですね。
Nico Nico Cho Party 2018, Virtual New Year's Eve, the anime "Virtual-san is Looking"...
濃いなあ。
Dense.
濃いですね。
It is.
来ましたね。
It's here.
そうなんですよ。いろんな形で我々にも関わってくる話ですが。
That's right. These stories involve us in various ways.
そうそうそうそう。そしてね、あの、ニコニコ超パーティー2018の映像があるということなのだ。
Right, right. And we have footage of Nico Nico Cho Party 2018.
うわ、いいの？
Wow, is it okay?
見たいなと思います。どうぞ！
I'd like to see it. Here you go!
はい、というわけでね。こちらニコニコ超パーティー、これさいたまスーパーアリーナ！
Yes, so, this is Nico Nico Cho Party. This is Saitama Super Arena!
うわあ！
Wow!
ということで、みんな出てるんですよ、ここ。
So, everyone is appearing here.
そうですね。
Right.
でで、なんか、こんな大きい場所でパフォーマンスしたの初めてだったから、
And, since it was my first time performing in such a large place...
ねえ、ねえ、緊張したんだよね。二人はどうだった？
Right? I was nervous. How about you two?
初めてでしたよ、私も。こんな大きい場所でやるの。
It was my first time too, performing in such a big place.
私か。めっちゃ緊張しましたよ。
Me? I was super nervous.
本当に。大人多い！って思って。
Really. "There are so many adults!" I thought.
大人多いよね。
Lots of adults.
私、「千本桜」を歌わせて頂いたんですけど、
I was allowed to sing "Senbonzakura",
歌ったら女の子の声もたくさん返ってきて、
and when I sang, lots of girls' voices came back to me,
「会場広！」っていう、なんかやり取りができたのが覚えてますね。
I remember that interaction of thinking "The venue is huge!"
確かに。
True.
そう、歓声とかあるとね、やっぱ嬉しくなるよね。
Yeah, hearing the cheers makes you happy.
ねえ。
Yeah.
まあ、2019年は、えー、ビクターエンタテインメントからメジャーデビューが決まったりだとか、
Well, in 2019, major debut from Victor Entertainment was decided,
あと「四月一日さん家の」っていうドラマに出させて頂いたりとか。
and I appeared in the drama "Watanuki-san Chi no".
三姉妹のね。
The three sisters one.
そうです、そうです。
Right, right.
あとはですね、あの、デビューアルバムがちょうどね、3月27日に発売されたりとか、
And then, the debut album was released on March 27th,
そういうことがありましての次なんですけど、
after those things, next is...
なんだろ、結構行くね。
What is it? Moving right along.
そして次がこちらですね。
And next is this.
「重大発表と大事なお知らせ、最後まで見てね」っていう放送だったんですけど、
It was a broadcast titled "Major Announcement and Important News, watch until the end"...
映像がありますので、何が重大発表だったのかちょっと見てもらいたいと思います。
We have footage, so I'd like you to see what the major announcement was.
見たいよ！最後だけ見ていいの？
I want to see! Is it okay to just see the end?
どうぞ！
Here you go!
やったー！
I did it!
というわけでですね、ここで、えー、1番...
So, here, the 1st...
あ、そう、ワンマンライブを決定したというのと、
Ah, right, deciding on the one-man live...
この時にちょっとお化粧ができるようになりまして、
and at this time, I became able to do some "makeup"...
お見事、えーちゃん。
Well done, A-chan.
おめでとう！
Congratulations!
まだえーちゃんがこの...ちょっと、絵心（えごころ）が成長しちゃったっていう重大発表。
A-chan's... like, the artistic heart grew a bit. That was the major announcement.
足がね。
The legs.
そう、色がついてね。ちょっと手もね、ちょっと進化しちゃったっていうね。
Yeah, getting colors. And the hands evolved a bit too.
まあ自分のお化粧、えーちゃんがちょっとお化粧がうまく。
Well, my "makeup", A-chan getting a bit better at "makeup".
あと、あの、ちょっとライブが決まったみたいな、こういろんな重大発表。
And also, a live being decided, various major announcements.
ほうほうほうほう。
I see, I see.
あーあったときということで
So, that's when it was.
そらちゃんって言ったらやっぱりステージで
When I think of Sora-chan, she's on stage,
アイドルとして歌って魅了してっていう印象がもうしっかり確立されてるので
singing as an idol and captivating everyone.
That image is already well-established.
そうですよね。
That's true.
まあここがときのそらちゃんの一人の重大なステージの発表場だったんだなあって
So this was the place for one of Tokino
Sora-chan's major stage announcements.
大事な日付ですね。
It's an important date.
そうですね。なんかここはやっぱり応援してくれてるそらともさんもなんか
Right. I think for the Soratomo
who have been supporting me,
6月27日になると
when June 27th comes around,
最初から応援してくれてるファンの人は色々思い出すみたいな
fans who have supported me from the start
probably remember all sorts of things.
へー！
Whoa!
やっぱりそういうのもあるみたいなので。
It seems like there's that kind of feeling too.
ターニングポイント一つ目というか、まあ一つ目というか
It was like the first turning point,
well, maybe one of many,
色々あるのかもしれないけど一番大きかったかなと思いますね。
but I think it was the biggest one.
だってもう嬉しそうだもん、伝わってくるもん。
You look so happy, it really shows.
そんな2年目なんですけど、
Anyway, that was my second year, but
もうねある方からメッセージをいただいているので
we've received a message from someone,
ちょっとビデオデータ見てみたいなと思います！
so let's take a look at the video!
どうぞ、この方です！
Here she is!
ごきげんようでありんす！
Gokigen-yo!
地球人類さん！
Humans of Earth!
侵略宇宙人、銀河アリスです！
I'm the invading alien, Ginga Alice!
あいしゃあああ！
Aishaaaa!
そらちゃーん、そらちゃーん！
Sora-chan, Sora-chan!
100万人様こんにちわ記念おめでとうございやす！
Congratulations on reaching 1 million subscribers!
すごいよ！
It's amazing!
すごすぎるよ！
Too amazing!
100万人って何人ですか！？
How many people is 1 million!?
100万人のたくさんの人がそらちゃん大好きってことだけは
It's perfectly clear that 1 million people
バッチリ伝わってきてます。すごいです。
love Sora-chan. It's incredible.
あの、そらちゃんと初めてお会いした時、
When I first met Sora-chan,
緊張していたお銀を
I was so nervous,
とっても優しく包み込んでくださって、
but you were so kind to me,
秒でときめいたことを今でも覚えています。ありがとうございやす！
and I remember falling for you in a second.
Thank you so much!
VTuberLand Volume 1で初めてイベントさんにね、
We participated in our first event together
一緒に出場させていただいたんですけど
at VTuberLand Volume 1.
可愛くて、みんなに楽しんでもらいたいっていう気持ちに溢れた
Sora-chan's performance was so cute and full
そらちゃんのステージさんは最高すぎました！
of desire to make everyone happy. It was the best!
もう、最高オブ最高でした！
The best of the best!
なんかね、あのそらちゃんがお銀のダンスを見て
I was really happy to hear that Sora-chan
自分もダンスを頑張りたいって思ってくださったって聞いて本当に嬉しかったんですけど
saw my dancing and felt inspired to work hard
on her own dancing.
お銀も、あのそらちゃんの最強のお歌さんをこうすごく間近で聞いたりとか
I also got to hear Sora-chan's
amazing singing up close,
時に可愛く、
sometimes cute,
時にかっこよく、
sometimes cool,
もう伸び伸びそらちゃんが歌っている姿を見て
and seeing her sing so freely—
お歌さんを頑張りたいってお銀も思えた一つのきっかけだったので
was one of the reasons I wanted to work hard
on my own singing.
なんかさ、
So, like...
もう…すごいやん！
it's amazing!
また一緒にね、そらりすとしてステージさんに立たせていただきたいでありんす！
I'd love for us to stand on stage together
again as Sora-Alice!
そして、そらともの皆様！
And to all the Soratomo!
お銀もそらともですから、
I'm a Soratomo too,
これからも一緒にね、そらちゃんについていきやしょう！
so let's keep following Sora-chan together!
改めてそらちゃん、本当に本当におめでとうございやす！
Once again, Sora-chan, congratulations
from the bottom of my heart!
これからも素敵なところはずーっとそのままで、
Please stay as wonderful as you are,
この先さらにさらに進化していくお姿を近くで応援させてください！
and let me keep cheering you on from up close
as you evolve even further!
ずっとずっと大好きです！
I'll always, always love you!
それじゃあ、バイバーイ！
See ya, bye-bye!
ありがとうー！
Thank you!
元気でしたね！
She was so energetic!
元気だったね、
She really was,
すごいやん！
it's amazing!
銀河アリスちゃん！
Ginga Alice-chan!
幼馴染みたいな。
We're like childhood friends.
でも今の「すごいやん」っていうのはやっぱりいつものアリスちゃんがあっていいなと思った。
Hearing her say 'it's amazing' just now felt
so much like the usual Alice-chan, it was great.
アリスちゃんとはね、この今言ってたVTuberLandっていう
Alice-chan and I did our first joint
初めて一緒にタイバンみたいな感じでライブをさせていただいて
live-style event together at VTuberLand,
私のダンスを頑張ろうと思ったきっかけを作ってくれた子っていうのはあるし、
and she's the one who inspired me to work hard
すごい仲の良いお友達なので
on my dancing. We're very close friends.
なにに…ライブさんとか、「さん」つけるところがめちゃくちゃ可愛くて
Adding '-san' to everything, like 'live-san,'
is just so cute.
今回はメッセージをいただいちゃいました。ありがとうございます。
I'm so glad she sent us a message.
Thank you so much.
というわけで、2年目まで終わりましたが、
So, that wraps up the second year.
どうですかね、2年目まで。
What do you think about it so far?
むしろお伺いしてて思ったのが、多分ドラマの撮影もですけど、
Actually, hearing about it made me think...
between things like filming the drama,
ほぼ丸一日撮影にかけたり
you probably spent almost entire days on shoots.
そらともさんを喜ばせるための取り組みで
With everything you did to make
なんだかんだ睡眠時間も趣味の時間も取れてなかったんじゃないですか？
the Soratomo happy, I bet you barely had
time for sleep or hobbies, right?
でも二人だって、いっぱい色々出てて大変だった時期だったんじゃない？
But weren't you two also really busy back then,
appearing in so many things?
やっぱその辛さわかるのは我々っていうことで
I guess we're the ones who really understand
that struggle.
そうそうそう
True, true, true.
頑張っておいでー
Hang in there!
あ、これ捕まえてチャって
Oh, let me just grab you...
あ、ちょっと、ときときダンスしよう真ん中で
Ah, wait, let's do the Doki Doki Dance
in the middle!
ときときダンス！
Doki Doki Dance!
え？何、どこ行けばいいの？右と左にさあ
Wait, what? Where should I go?
On the left and right?
えー、これがときときダンス
Hehe, this is the Doki Doki Dance!
ときときー！ときときー！
Doki Doki! Doki Doki!
じゃあ、こんなときときダンスをしながら、今日、この回は終わりにしましょうかね。
Well, let's wrap up this segment while doing
the Doki Doki Dance.
ありがとうございました！
Thank you very much!
ときときっていいなー！
Doki Doki is so nice!
ときのそら年表 2年目 (2018年9月～2019年8月)
Tokino Sora Timeline: 2nd Year (Sep 2018 - Aug 2019)
おめでとうございます。
Congratulations.
ありがとうございます！
Thank you!
お気に入り、入るかい？
Will it be a favorite?
お二人とも、ありがとうございました。
Thank you both very much.
こちらこそ、ありがとうございました。
Likewise, thank you very much.
お二人にはね、後でもう一曲歌ってもらおうと思ってますから。
I'm planning to have the two of you sing another song later.
よろしくお願いします。
Looking forward to it.
バイバイ！
Bye bye!
それではこのテンションで後半に向かいます。
And with this high energy, we'll move on to the second half.
うわー！
Whoo!
はい！というわけで後半パートは、YuNiちゃんと葵ちゃんです！
All right! So for the second half, we have YuNi-chan and Aoi-chan!
イエーイ！
Yay!
富士葵です。
It's Fuji Aoi.
YuNiです。
It's YuNi.
やってる？
Are you doing well?
隠されてる、隠されてる。
I'm being hidden, I'm being hidden.
はい、というわけでね、ここからは3年目、2019年あたりからをね、
Yes, so. From here on, we'll look at the 3rd year, around 2019.
ちょっと近づいてきましたね。
We're getting closer.
ちょっと近づいてきましたね。見ていきたいと思いますので、
We're getting closer. I'd like to take a look, so...
じゃあ早速、3年目のパネル見てみましょう。こちらです！
Then let's right away look at the 3rd year panel. Here it is!
ときのそら年表 3年目 (2019年9月～2020年8月)
Tokino Sora Timeline: 3rd Year (Sep 2019 - Aug 2020)
2020/5/15 初の作詞作曲楽曲「青空のシンフォニー」MV公開
2020/05/15 First self-composed song "Aozora no Symphony" MV released
まぁ3年目はね、ちょっとあれなんですよ。あのね、ほら、
Well, the 3rd year was a bit... you know. Well, look,
世界でもいろんなことがあって、いろんなものが変わった時代ということで。
it was a time when many things happened in the world and many things changed.
ちょっとね、ちょっと少なめの表示には今なってるんですけども。
So the display is a bit sparse right now.
なりますなぁ。
It happens.
まぁね、そんな中で2019年にあったものがね、あるのでちょっとそれを見たいと思います。
Well, among all that, there's something from 2019, so I'd like to look at that.
それがこちらです！
Here it is!
2019/10/6 初のワンマンライブ Dream! 開催
2019/10/06 First one-man live "Dream!" held
10月6日にね、初のワンマンライブ「Dream!」があったんですけども、
On October 6th, my first one-man live "Dream!" was held,
なんとね、これ前日にお二人がライブをしてるんですよね。
but surprisingly, the two of you had a live performance the day before.
そうなんですよ！
That's right!
昼の部を...
The afternoon show...
昼の部やって、5日の昼の部、夜の部、次の日、みたいな感じでね。
We did the afternoon show, the afternoon and evening shows on the 5th, and then the next day.
連続でっていうのがすごい話題になった。
It became a big topic, doing it back-to-back.
そうね。
Yeah.
だからなんかね、そこすごい一致団結してた感じあるよね。
So there was a real sense of unity there.
よっしゃ頑張ろうって。
Like, "All right, let's do this!"
事務所分かれてるけど、一緒！みたいな。
Even though we're in different agencies, we're together!
すごいしましたね。
We really did.
本当にそうだった。
It really was like that.
あの、リハとかさ、
Like, during rehearsals...
結構、時間、あの、被ることがあって。
our times would often overlap.
そう、で特にここ一緒だったからさ、日にちが。
Yeah, especially because the dates were so close.
だからなんか、YuNiがリハ終わった後に葵がリハとかあって。
So YuNi would finish rehearsal and then Aoi would start.
そん時にさ、まぁ一個話すならば、
At that time, if I were to share one story,
なんかYuNiが一瞬ちょっとハケたんだよね、ステージから。
YuNi stepped off the stage for a moment.
で戻ったら、なんかちょっとあの、
And when I came back, well,
YuNiの髪の毛なくなってて。
my hair was gone.
髪の毛がなくなった。
Her hair was gone.
そう。つるつるになっちゃって頭が。
Yeah. My head became totally bald.
で、それを葵に見せて、
And I showed it to Aoi,
「見て、頭つるつるになった」って言ったら、
and said, "Look, my head went bald,"
「体張りすぎだろ」って言って。
and she was like, "You're going too far for the bit!"
バトンタッチしたことあったね。
That was when we swapped.
We did have that handoff.
その後そらちゃんがやるっていう。
And then Sora-chan was going to perform after.
そうそう。
Right, right.
だから、もしかしたら、もうちょっとで、そらちゃんも、ちょっと頭つるつるになったかもしれない。
So maybe, if it had gone on a bit longer, Sora-chan might have also gone a bit bald.
本当に？そういう魔法にかかっちゃってたとしたら。
Really? If I had fallen under that kind of spell...
じゃあね、そういうのかかってるかどうか当時の映像を見てみましょう。
Well then, let's look at the footage from back then to see if I was.
おー！見たい！
Oh! I want to see!
はい、こちらです。どうぞ！
All right, here it is. Please!
♪ 好き、泣いちゃいそうだ
♪ Suki, Naichai Sou Da
ミニアルバム「My Loving!」 2020.3.4 Release
Mini album "My Loving!" 2020.03.04 Release
うわー！
Whoo!
これ、ここでやったね！
This, we did it here!
やったー、本当に！
We did it, really!
さすがチッタだよなぁ。
As expected of Citta.
この場所ね、すごい人が、もうぎゅうぎゅうだった。
This place, it was packed with people.
ぎゅうぎゅうで大丈夫かなって思いながら。
I was wondering if it would be okay since it was so packed.
すごかったんだよね。熱かったんだよ、10月なのに。
It was amazing. It was hot, even though it was October.
あ、そうそう。待ってる人たちもね、
Oh, right. Even the people waiting...
今日、すごい列になってもらって。
today, there was a huge line.
みんなすごくなんか助け合って、ライブに楽しんでもらえてて、すごかった。
Everyone was helping each other out and enjoying the live, it was great.
そうだった。
That's right.
かわいい。
So cute.
エモいね。
So emotional.
うわー！いい！いい！
Wow! Great! Great!
歓声の聞こえる感じ、ね。
The sound of the cheering, you know.
わーってね。
Like "Whooo."
なんか初めてワンマンやって、あ、もっと歌っていきたいなって私は思ったんだよね。
After doing my first one-man live, I felt like I wanted to keep singing more and more.
あー、嬉しい。
Oh, that's good.
いい日じゃん。いい日じゃん。
It was a good day. A great day.
もう最高の思い出の日。
It's a day of the best memories.
ベスト5に入る、あの、5年間で。
It's in my top 5 from these 5 years.
10月6日、ベスト5に入ります。
October 6th is in the top 5.
入りますよ、もちろん。
Of course it is.
夢だったからね、ライブやるの。
Because performing a live show was my dream.
初ワンマン。しかもね。
And the first one-man live, at that.
そしてね、この3年目なんですけど、
And also, about this 3rd year,
ビデオレターが、あるお方から届いているということで。
a video message has arrived from someone.
誰？
Who?
ちょっと見てみたいと思います。こちらです！
I'd like to take a look. Here it is!
とき、の、そらちゃん！
Toki, no, Sora-chan!
イエーイ！てんきゅっ！でんっ！
Yay! Thank you! Bam!
そらちゃん、100万人おめでとう！
Sora-chan, congratulations on 1 million!
いや、本当にめちゃめちゃ感慨深いです、私。
No, really, I'm deeply moved.
なんか、そらちゃんとは、めちゃめちゃ長いんですよ。
Well, Sora-chan and I have known each other for a very long time.
色々とね。長いんですけど。
In various ways. It's been a long time.
ちょうどいつだったかな。
I wonder exactly when it was.
そらちゃんが、30万人行ったぐらいの時かな。
Maybe around the time Sora-chan reached 300,000 subscribers.
多分、30万人行ったかなっていう時ぐらいに、
Probably around the time she hit 300,000,
なんか...
well...
そらちゃんがちょっと悩み事があるよーって言ってて、
Sora-chan said she had some worries...
そん時に、私も
and at that time, I also...
あんまり伸びないかもしれないからVTuber続けていけるかなーって
"I'm not sure if I can continue as a VTuber because I might not grow much."
悩んでた時があったんですよ、そらちゃんは。
Sora-chan had a time when she was worried like that.
そん時に、
At that time...
そらちゃんは絶対にこのVTuberのこの界隈を引っ張っていける存在になるし、
I said, "Sora-chan will definitely become someone who can lead this VTuber scene,"
100万人とか絶対超えちゃうような存在だから、
"and you're someone who will definitely exceed 1 million subscribers,"
私を信じて続けてよーって
"so believe in me and keep going."
言ったことがあったんですけど、
I remember saying that to her.
本当に100万人超えてる！
And now she's actually over 1 million!
すごいよ本当に。
It's really amazing.
めちゃめちゃ嬉しいし、
I'm so incredibly happy,
あの時いっぱい、いっぱい引き止めてよかったなって
and I'm so glad I stopped you so many times back then.
本当に思います。
I really feel that way.
でもね、まだまだ始まったばっかだよね、
But, you know, it's still just the beginning,
ときのそらはきっと。
for Tokino Sora, I'm sure.
ここからもっともっと、120万とか30万とか、50万とか、200万とか。
From here, more and more—1.2M, 1.3M, 1.5M, 2M.
私は行けると信じていますので、
I believe you can do it,
末長く、末長くね、
so for a long, long time to come,
私たちのVTuberという世界を引っ張る一人として、走り続けてください。
please keep running as one of the leaders of our VTuber world.
私はそんなそらちゃんに信じていっぱい付いていきますから、
I'll believe in you and follow you anywhere,
いつまでもおそばにおりますゆえ。
so I'll always be by your side.
神様のご加護がついてますよ。シュッ！
God's protection is with you. *Swish!*
改めてそらちゃん、おめでとう！
Once again, Sora-chan, congratulations!
私にとってそらちゃんは大事な、大事なお友達です。
To me, Sora-chan is a very, very precious friend.
これからもいっぱい、いっぱいニコニコ幸せに笑っててね。
Please keep smiling happily with a big grin from now on too.
以上、天神子兎音でした。
That's all from Tenjin Kotone.
アイラブユー！チュッチュッチュ。
I love you! *Kiss kiss kiss*
ほうー
Whoa—
はい、というわけで、
Yes, and with that...
天神、ユリがちょっと、涙出てきちゃったんだけど。
Tenjin— Yuuri is a bit tearing up right now.
ちょっとユリエ隊長、涙出てきちゃったね。
Commander Yuuri is starting to cry, isn't she?
本当に。
Really.
待って、ここ3人はね、子兎音ちゃんのことすごいよく知ってるから。
Wait, the three of us know Kotone-chan very well.
そうだねー。
That's true.
なんか、こんな真面目なメッセージが来てると思ってなかったので、
I didn't expect such a serious message to come,
ちょっと動揺はしてるんですけど。
so I'm a bit shaken.
いや、すごいなんか、そのー悩みを相談してて、
No, it's amazing how you consulted her with your worries,
そっからこう勇気づけられたっていう二人の関係とかね、
and how the two of you have that kind of relationship where she encouraged you...
あったんだね、そんなことが。
I didn't know that happened.
あったんだね、やっぱり最初の頃とかはやっぱりね、どうしてもやっぱり、
It did. Especially in the beginning, naturally...
ちょっとずつでも、みんなもだけど、伸びてっててても、
even if I was growing little by little, like everyone else,
これがいつまで続くのかとかわかんないし。
I didn't know how long it would last.
この3年目に入ってくるとやっぱりね、継続になっちゃってるから。
Entering the 3rd year, it becomes about "continuation."
そうそう。
Exactly.
新しいこと、なんなんだろうみたいに思う時期だったから、
It was a time when I wondered, "What new things can I do?"
わかるわかる。
I get it, I get it.
ちょっとね、そういう意味ではね、色々悩んだ時期、悩みの時期だったかなとは思いますね。
In that sense, I think it was a time when I worried a lot.
ちょうどこの時期に辞めるか辞めないかみたいな考えも、
Right around that time, I even had thoughts about...
ちょうどあった時期でもあったから。
whether to quit or not.
そういう意味ではすごく、いやー、よかったよね、続けてきてくれて本当に。
In that sense, I'm really, really glad you kept going.
よくやった、天神よく止めたなー。
Well done. Kotone did a great job stopping you.
本当だよね。
She really did.
Soraともしたもんね、安心してると思うけど。
The Sora-tomo must be relieved too.
うんうんうん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
それでは4年目行ってみましょう。こちらです。
Now, let's look at the 4th year. Here it is.
はい。
Okay.
おーいっぱいある。目白押しですね、この年は。
Oh, there's a lot. It was a packed year.
そうだね。
It was.
まず一つ目がこちらです。
First of all, this one.
ここでね、まあ、あおいちゃんも色々お化粧勉強してたくさん、
Here, well, Aoi-chan also studied makeup a lot,
そらちゃんと一緒に、お化粧進化していくというか。
and together with Sora-chan, our "makeup" evolved.
懐かしい。
How nostalgic.
そうだよ、私たちはね、どんどんね、成長するもの、勉強しましたよ。
That's right. We studied because we want to keep growing.
勉強しましたよ。
We certainly did.
そして私がね、ちょっとね、お化粧進化しすぎて、
And then I evolved my makeup a bit too much...
普段のメイクがやばすぎるっていう。
and my usual makeup became crazy.
勉強したけどね、放送用のね。
I studied for the broadcasts, though.
放送用の勉強したけど、普段のね。
Studies for broadcasts, but the usual one...
頑張りましたねということで、
Well, we worked hard on that.
そして次のところがこちらです。はい。
And here's the next point. Yes.
おー、ここで50万人言ってる！
Oh, it says 500,000 here!
すごーい！早いねー。
Amazing! That was fast.
やーびっくりした。
Wow, I'm surprised.
私もこれね、あの、さっき見せてもらって、やっと気づいたんですよ。
I only just realized this when I was shown it earlier.
あ、ここで50万なんだって。
"Oh, so it was 500,000 here."
早いねー。
It's fast.
早ー。
So fast.
やっぱりこれは、なんか、なんて言うんだろう、
After all, this is, how should I say...
いろんなところからグローバルに見に来てくださることが増えたからっていうのもあるし、
partly because more people started coming to watch globally from all over,
そういうそらともさんたちが、そらちゃんってこんなに、
and also because those Sora-tomo...
こういうことやってるんだよって今までのまとめとかをツイートとかで、
wrote tweets summarizing what Sora-chan has done so far,
知らない人向けに書いてくれてたりとかもしたんだよね。
for people who didn't know about me yet.
だから、そういうのもあったからみんなの力で、
So, with all of that, with everyone's power...
50万人にしていただいたっていう感じがすごくしますね。
I really feel like you all brought me to 500,000.
もうもっと、あれだね、そらともがワールドワイドというか、
It's more like the Sora-tomo are worldwide,
ときのそらが、ときそらがワールドワイドになった瞬間なんですかね。
or maybe it's the moment Tokino Sora—Tokisora—went worldwide.
もう、そらときの、ですね。
It's Sora Tokino now.
そうですね、名前が逆になって。
That's right, the name is reversed.
素晴らしいね。
Wonderful.
確かに素晴らしい。
Certainly wonderful.
はい、そして、そんな私の、次の出来事が、こちら！
Yes! And, the next event for me is this!
ときのそら年表 4年目 (2020年9月〜2021年8月)
2021/3/3 私服新衣装お披露目
Tokino Sora Timeline: Year 4 (Sept 2020 - Aug 2021)
2021/3/3 New casual outfit reveal
この時にね、私服、初めてお披露目しました。
At this time, I revealed my casual outfit for the first time.
めっちゃ好き、私服。
I really like it, the casual outfit.
じゃあ、その映像もあるので、
Well, since we have the footage,
見よう、見よう、見よう！
Let's watch it! Let's watch!
行きましょうかね！
Let's go, shall we?
どうぞ！
Here you go!
うわ〜、マジ可愛かった！
Whoa, that was seriously cute!
私服ね、初めての...
The casual outfit, the first time...
焦らされてるよ。
I'm being teased.
焦らされてるね。だったと思うんだけど。
You were being teased. I think so.
早く、早く！
Hurry, hurry!
まだ足しかねえ！
Only the feet so far!
足、足。あの角度。
Feet, feet. That angle.
お〜！
Oh~!
普段はね、髪下ろしてないから、ポニテなんだけど。
Usually, I don't have my hair down, it's a ponytail.
待ったかな？
Did I keep you waiting?
ほんとに？あ〜よかった。
Really? Ah, good.
今来たとこだったら、デート風の配信をね。
If you just arrived, it's a date-style stream.
ねぇねぇ見て、今日さ、
Hey, hey look, today,
せっかくのお出かけの日だから、ちょっとね、おしゃれしてきたんだよね。
since it's a special day for going out, I dressed up a bit.
可愛い？
Is it cute?
どこ行こうかな〜？
Where should we go?
可愛い、可愛い、可愛い！
Cute, cute, cute!
マジで見たかった、これ。
I really wanted to see this.
そうだね、ちょっと今もう、こう、見惚れちゃってたもんね、我々ね。
Yeah, we were just totally captivated by it, weren't we?
私服はなんか、こういうのがいいな、みんなの前に出すにはっていうのはあったの？
Regarding the casual outfit, did you have an idea of what you wanted to wear for everyone?
あったあった。普段私はこういう服が好きだから、
Yes, I did. I like these kinds of clothes normally,
だから私の私服は、なんか普段の私で出たいって言って仕立ててもらった。
so I asked for it to be made so I could show the "everyday me" in my casual outfit.
あ〜、素のときのそらを曝け出しちゃったってことじゃない？
So, you basically bared the real Tokino Sora, right?
そう、だから、コンタクトせずに、茶色の目で。
Exactly. So, I went without contacts, with my natural brown eyes.
そう！それを私、忘れてた！そう、青い目じゃない！
That's right! I forgot about that! Right, not blue eyes!
放送見ながら、あ！って言ったわ、私。
While watching the broadcast, I went "Ah!"
限界、限界さん、コンタクトしてない！って。
I was like "Wait, she's not wearing contacts!"
そんなこの年は、なので、結構お化粧とか衣装を頑張った年だったんだよね。
So, this was a year where I put a lot of effort into things like makeup and outfits.
そうだね、確かに。
True, indeed.
最後は、ちょっとね、あおちゃんに関係あることが…こちらです！
Lastly, there's something related to Ao-chan... here it is!
初めてメッセージ動画をいただいて、動画に合わせてパフォーマンスする記念配信をやったんですよ。
For the first time, I received message videos and did a commemorative broadcast where I performed along with them.
やっぱりこう、色々あって、みんなで集まるのがちょっとまだ難しいねって、2021年の時期は、だったので、
Well, with everything going on in 2021, it was a time when gathering everyone together was still difficult.
メッセージとパフォーマンスの動画を先にいただいて、それをスクリーンに出して、それに合わせてパフォーマンスをするっていう演出をしたんです。
So, I received the message and performance videos beforehand, showed them on the screen, and performed along with them.
おしゃれなコラボ！後ろのスクリーンに出させてもらってっていう出演の仕方は、確かに、なかったもんね、今まで。
What a stylish collab! Being featured on the screen in the background like that was something we hadn't seen before.
新しくて。私の中では、やっぱり、いろんな人と一緒に記念配信をしたいっていう気持ちはあるけど、
It was fresh. For me, I really wanted to do a commemorative broadcast with various people,
でも、その場には、ちょっと…ってなったら、やっぱりこれでしょう！と思ってやったのと、
but since having them there in person was difficult, I thought "this is the way!" and did it.
その時に、あおいちゃんのメッセージだけ、めちゃくちゃ気合が入ってて。
And at that time, Aoi-chan's message alone was incredibly enthusiastic.
メッセージ動画をコテコテに編集して、出させていただいたんですけど、
I sent a message video that I'd edited to the max,
すごいそらちゃんが笑ってくれて、よかった、本当。
and Sora-chan laughed a lot at it, so I'm really glad.
ものまねしたんだっけ？
Did you do an impression?
ものまねしたのに、ものまね直前でカットされてる...
I did an impression, but it was cut right before the impression started...
全然似てなくて、見るに耐えなかったから切りました。そうだそうだ。
It wasn't similar at all and was unbearable to watch, so it was cut. Right, right.
そんな感じで、4年目も終わったんですが、
And with that, the 4th year ended,
ここで、ある方からお手紙が、来ております！
but we've received a letter from a certain person!
私服を始め、たくさんの衣装をデザインしてくださっている、おるだん先生からです！
It's from Orudan-sensei, who has designed many of my outfits, including the casual one!
読ませていただきたいと思います。
I would like to read it.
そらちゃん、100万人おめでとうございます！
Sora-chan, congratulations on 1 million subscribers!
初めてそらちゃんの公式ビジュアルを描き上げた時、
When I first finished drawing Sora-chan's official visual,
空高く掲げた手に、どこまでも高く伸びやかに、活躍していく姿を願いに描きました。
I drew you with your hand raised high, wishing for you to soar ever higher and thrive.
あの時は果てしなく遠い道のりで、自分にとってもどこか子供っぽい夢だったのかもしれませんが、
Back then, it seemed like an endless journey, and for me, it might have been a somewhat childish dream,
伸ばした手の先が、今こうして100万人に届いて、こんな風に夢が叶うことがあるんだって噛み締めてます。
but seeing your outstretched hand now reach 1 million people, I'm reflecting on how dreams can come true.
一端ですが、関わるものとして、すごく嬉しいです！
Even if in a small way, as someone involved, I am very happy!
どうぞこれからも伸びやかに、そして、そらちゃんのペースに歩んでいってくださいね。
Please continue to grow freely and walk at your own pace.
今後のご活躍をお祈りしております。おるだん、ということで。
I pray for your continued success. Signed, Orudan.
ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
今のお手紙も、すごい泣ける内容で。すいちゃんどうですか？涙出てます？
That letter was so touching. Suichan, how about you? Are you in tears?
半分ぐらいかな？
Maybe about half?
優しい、おるだん先生は、
Orudan-sensei is so kind.
本当に全部の衣装を、今も描いていただいて、
Truly, he has designed all my outfits up to now,
いろんな衣装仕立てていただいたり、こんなデザインだよって見せてくださる方なので、本当に今の私の、
and he's the one who tailors various outfits and shows me designs, so he's truly responsible for my current...
ときのそら年表 4年目 (2020年9月〜2021年8月)
Tokino Sora Timeline: Year 4 (Sep 2020 - Aug 2021)
もう全てをこうわかってくださってる皆さんの好みとかもね、そうですね。
You all understand everything about me now, including my preferences.
するので、こうやってね、こう言っていただけると、ますます気合が入りますね。
Knowing that you say things like that gives me even more motivation.
これからも頑張っていきたいと思います。ありがとうございます。
I'll continue to do my best from here on out. Thank you so much.
ありがとうございます、先輩！
Thank you so much, Senpai!
素晴らしいです。イェーイ！
You're amazing. Yay!
そしてそして、5年目、ここまでですね。を行ってみたいと思います。
And now, let's take a look at the 5th year, which brings us to the present.
早い！はい！5年目はこちらです！ほい！
So fast! All right! Here is the 5th year! There!
ときのそら年表 5年目 (2021年9月〜2022年8月)
Tokino Sora Timeline: Year 5 (Sep 2021 - Aug 2022)
おおー！なんかめっちゃ光ってる一箇所！
Oh! One part is really shining!
色が違う！一箇所めちゃめちゃ光ってるんですけど！
The color is different! There's one part that's shining like crazy!
何でしょう？
I wonder what it is?
まあね、何でしょうね。ま、その前にね、前には、ま、この年は色んなアーティストさんとのコラボが多かった年ではあって。
Well, let's see. Before that, this year had many collaborations with various artists.
そうですね。で、初めてね、この一番上に書いてあるのはホラーゲームのお化け役みたいのやったんですよね。
That's right. And for the first time, as written at the top, I played the role of a ghost in a horror game.
そうそうそう、私ホラーゲームは大好きで、お化け役でみんな驚かせたい願望があったので。
Yes, I love horror games, and I've always wanted to try scaring people as a ghost.
あー、すごーい。あの顔が好きです。
Oh, wow. I love that face you made.
そう、めっちゃいい顔してるんで、そうすごい、いい顔してるんだよね。
Yeah, you had a really great expression there.
わかるわかる、みんな好きだと思う、あの表情。
I know, I know. I think everyone loves that look on your face.
そしてそして、あの金の場所、めちゃめちゃ光ってる、何で色が違うの？こちらです！
And then, that golden spot. It's shining so much! Why is the color different? Here it is!
この7月27日に、100万人突破いたしました！
On July 27th, I reached 1 million subscribers!
おめでとうございます！おめでとうございます！
Congratulations! Congratulations!
いや、でも私はユニちゃんたちもすごいと思ってるの。
But I think you and the others are amazing too, Yuuni-chan.
やっぱり、あの、一人でずっとやってきてるじゃない。私には後輩がいっぱいいて、そう仲間がいっぱいいてっていう状況だけど。
After all, you've been doing this on your own for a long time. I have many juniors and friends around me.
でも、ソロでずっと活躍し続けるってそんな簡単じゃないし。
But continuing to be active as a solo artist isn't easy at all.
ソロでアーティストとして毎年ライブができるなんてなかなかないから。
Being able to hold live concerts every year as a solo artist is quite rare.
やっぱりそういう意味で、やっぱ二人はすごいよって思う。
In that sense, I really think you two are incredible.
ときのそら、友達、やめないでね。
Tokino Sora, please don't stop being our friend.
え、もちろんやめないよ！私、友達少ないからずっと友達でいて。
Of course I won't! I don't have many friends, so please stay my friend forever.
やめないでね、こちらこそ、これからもよろしくお願いします。
Don't stop, okay? I should be the one saying that. I look forward to working with you from now on.
ろしくお願いします、先輩！みんなずっと友達だよ！
We look forward to it too, Senpai! We'll always be friends!
そして、じゃあ最後行きますか、最後はこちら！
And now, let's move on to the last one. The last one is this!
あ、2022年9月7日、5周年のお祝い記念日に、
On September 7th, 2022, our 5th anniversary celebration day...
5周年記念アルバムを、同時に発売しました！
...we released a 5th anniversary album at the same time!
おめでたい、おめでたい！
What a celebratory occasion! So festive!
5年間こんなに続けられることって、あんまり想像してなかったじゃない。
I never really imagined I'd be able to continue for 5 years like this.
本当だ、本当にそうだ。
You're right. That's so true.
なんか意外と5年っていけるんだなって思った。
I realized that 5 years is actually doable.
そうだね、あっという間、でもそれぐらいやっぱ濃かったんだろうね、みんなそれぞれ。
Yeah, it went by in a flash. But that just shows how dense and meaningful it was for everyone.
見えてないから、あのキラキラで、お顔隠れて。
I can't see you! Your face is hidden behind those sparkles.
これからもやっぱり、ずっと初期から一緒に友達として仲良くしてくれてる二人と。
From now on, I want to continue being friends with you two, who have been with me since the early days.
もちろんね、前に出た二人もそうだけど、ずっとずっと一緒に活動して、ずっと仲良く友達でいたいから。
And of course, the same goes for the two who were here earlier. I want us to keep working together and be friends forever.
これからも私と仲良くしてくれますか？
Will you continue to be my friends from here on out?
もちろんです！公私ともにね！いいとも！
Of course! Both professionally and personally! Definitely!
またご飯行こう！行きましょう！ね！
Let's go eat again! Let's do it! Definitely.
普通にご飯行いたりするからね。そうそうそう、ね、最近行けてないけどね。
We often go out to eat normally, after all. Right, right. We haven't been able to lately, though.
ちょっとゆっくりお話をしよう！しようしましょう！
Let's take our time and have a good chat! Let's do it!
というわけで、たくさんおしゃべりもしてしまいましたが、ここで終わりにしましょう、ときのそら年表でしたー！
Well then, we've talked a lot, but let's end it here. That was the Tokino Sora Timeline!
イェーイ！おめでとー！この後は！
Yay! Congratulations! And after this...
おっ、みんなで！もう一曲ライブしちゃおー！イェーイ！
Oh, let's all do one more live performance together! Yay!
さあ、ステージに移動するぞー！移動するよー！イェーイ！
All right, we're moving to the stage! Here we go! Yay!
ブラック★ロックシューター
Black Rock Shooter
どこへ行ったの？
Where did you go?
聞こえますか？
Can you hear me?
あとどれだけ叫べばいいんだろう？
How much more do I have to shout?
あとどれだけ...
How much more...
叫ばなければいいんだろ
If I don't have to scream...
もうやめて 私はもう走れない
Stop it, I can't run anymore.
いつか夢見た世界が閉じる
The world I once dreamed of is closing.
真っ暗で明かりもない
It's pitch black, with no light.
崩れかけたこの道で
On this crumbling road.
あるはずもないあの時の希望が
The hope from that time that shouldn't exist...
見えた気がした
...I felt like I saw it.
どうして ブラック★ロックシューター 懐かしい記憶
Why, Black Rock Shooter, nostalgic memories...
ただ楽しかったあの頃を
...of those times when it was just fun.
ブラック★ロックシューター でも動けないよ
Black Rock Shooter, but I can't move.
闇を駆ける星に願いを
A wish to the star that runs through the darkness.
もう一度だけ走るから
I'll run just one more time.
怖くて震える声でつぶやく
Whispering with a voice trembling in fear.
私の名前を呼んで
Call my name.
夜明けを抱く空 境界線までの距離
The sky embracing the dawn, the distance to the horizon.
あともう一歩届かない
One more step, but I can't reach it.
こらえた涙があふれそうなの
The tears I've held back are about to overflow.
今下を向かないで止まってしまう
Don't look down now, or everything will stop.
未来を生きていたいんだ わかったの
I want to live in the future, I understand now.
思いだして 強く 強く 信じるの
Remember, believe strongly, strongly.
そうよ ブラック★ロックシューター 優しい匂い
That's right, Black Rock Shooter, a gentle scent.
痛いよ 辛いよ 飲み込む言葉
It hurts, it's hard, the words I swallow.
ブラック★ロックシューター 動いてこの足!
Black Rock Shooter, move these legs!
世界を越えて
Beyond the world.
最初からわかっていた
I knew it from the start.
ここにいることを
Being here.
私の中のすべての勇気が
All the courage inside me...
火をともして
...lights the fire.
もう逃げないよ
I won't run away anymore.
ブラック★ロックシューター 一人じゃないよ
Black Rock Shooter, you're not alone.
声をあげて泣いたって構わない
It's okay to cry out loud.
ブラック★ロックシューター 見ていてくれる
Black Rock Shooter, you're watching over me.
今から始まるの 私の物語
My story starts from now.
忘れそうになったら
If I'm about to forget...
この歌を歌うの
...I'll sing this song.
はい、というわけで、ブラック★ロックシューターを歌わせていただきました！
Yes! So, we performed Black Rock Shooter!
わー！ありがとうございましたー！
Yay! Thank you very much!
いや、みんなでこの曲をどうしても歌いたくって...
I really wanted to sing this song with everyone...
みんな歌ってくれないかなーって頼んだんだよね。
I asked if they would sing it.
そしたらみんながこんなに綺麗に今日パフォーマンスしてくれて...
And then they gave such a beautiful performance today...
私はもう今、幸せでいっぱいです！
I'm just so happy right now!
めっちゃかっこよかったー！
It was so cool!
最高だったよー！
It was the best!
超気持ちよかったね、みんなで歌わせてもらって。
It felt so good to sing it together.
そしてね、今回こう、2、3で分かれて歌う場所もあったりしましたよね！
And also, there were parts where we split into groups of two and three to sing!
そうそうそう、ありましたよね！
Right, right, there were!
その場所はね、あの、この二人がなんかこう、カップルじゃないんだけど、なんか...
In those parts, these two were like... well, not a couple, but like...
えー！？好き！みたいな！
Eh!? Like "I love you!" or something!
（笑い声）
(Laughter)
当たり当たり！
Spot on, spot on!
5年経っても緊張してるのでやめてください！
I'm still nervous even after 5 years, so please stop!
それで、ぜひ二人で歌ってほしいって思って、
And so, I really wanted you two to sing together,
そう、パートをね、分けたんですよ。
so I split up the parts.
あ、そうだったんだ！
Oh, so that's how it was!
みとちゃん由礼乃のこと好きになったでしょ、今日。
Mito-chan, you've come to like Yuuri today, haven't you?
あ、委員長ですか？
Oh, the Class President?
ガチで、ガチで、もう本当にお気に入りで！
Seriously, seriously, she's really my favorite now!
みと先輩、由礼と仲良くなってくれましたよね？
Mito-senpai, you've become friends with Yuuri, right?
でもそらちゃんのおかげで、
But thanks to Sora-chan...
なんか本当に、一つもギスギスしていない素敵な空間であり...
it's really become such a wonderful space without any friction...
そうだよ、この前にもね、みんなで思い出を振り返ったりもしたじゃん。
That's right, and before this, we all looked back at our memories too.
多分見てる人もすごい懐かしいみたいなことたくさんあったんじゃないかな。
I'm sure the viewers also had many moments of feeling very nostalgic.
本当にさ、人に歴史ありだよね。
Really, everyone has their own history, don't they?
本当に今日、こんな素敵な一日になったのは、
The reason today has become such a wonderful day is
ここで一緒にパフォーマンスをしてくれた大切な仲間のみんな、
because of all my precious friends who performed here with me,
そして応援してくれてるそらともさんの、みんなのおかげだと思っています。
and all the Sora-tomo who have been supporting me.
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
そんな素敵なみんなはですね、なんとYouTubeをやってるのでぜひ...
These wonderful people, they all do YouTube, so please...
YouTubeやってるんですか！？
You guys do YouTube!?
え、すごい！YouTuberだ！
Wow, amazing! You're YouTubers!
由礼たちさ、終わったあとゼロ一個増えてる？
Yuuri and the others, did your subscriber counts gain another zero after this?
はい、というわけでこのあとはですね、今度出るEPっていう...
All right, so after this, from the EP coming out soon...
CDがあるんですけど、
well, it's a CD,
その中に入る曲を今回ここで初披露させていただきます！
I'll be performing a song from it for the first time right here!
はい、こちらはですね、その曲なので一人で歌わせていただきますが、
Yes, so I'll be singing this song solo, but
本当に初めてのみんなのことを思って作ったバラードなので、
it's a ballad I made thinking about all of you for the first time,
ぜひぜひ、よろしくお願いします。作っていただいたんですけど。
so please, I hope you enjoy it. Well, it was made for me.
というわけで今日は本当に見に来てくれて、
So, thank you so much for coming to see me today,
そして一緒にパフォーマンスしてくれてありがとうございました！
and thank you for performing together with me!
「キセキノセカイ」
Miracle World
キセキのような　君と作るメモリー
A memory like a miracle, made with you
ギュッと握りしめ　願ったよ
I gripped it tight and made a wish
きっと開花する　わくわくの新芽
The exciting buds will surely bloom
この場所が　初めての
This place is the first...
紡ぐ道標
...signpost we spin
ちょっとずつでも　踏み出してみて
Take a step, even if it's just a little at a time
幸せはすぐ　そばにあるものだから
Because happiness is something that's right beside you
怖がらないで　夢中になる
Don't be afraid to get absorbed
その力を　ほら　You...
That power, look, you...
この胸に花　咲かせてみせるよ
I'll make flowers bloom in this heart
何よりも強い　いのちの息吹
A breath of life stronger than anything
涙は未来の　水たまりになるから
Because tears will become puddles of the future
隣で拭いてあげる
I'll wipe them away beside you
信じてあすが　積もる未来
Believe in the future where tomorrows pile up
みんなへ
To everyone
ラララ 口ずさむ 安らぎは
Lalala, the peace I hum...
足跡が語る 証の結晶で
With the crystal of proof that our footprints tell...
次は君がいるから
Because you're here next...
きっと歩み出せるんだね
I'm sure we can start walking...
一歩ずつから 始めてみるよ
I'll try starting one step at a time
一緒に過ごして 宝物より尊い
Spending time together, more precious than treasure
夢の続きを 叶えていこう
Let's make the rest of the dream come true
伝えていこう with you
Let's keep conveying it, with you
散らばった 時の欠片 数え
Counting the scattered fragments of time
チグハグだった 響き集めれば
If we gather the mismatched echoes...
ほら 新しい世界
Look, a new world
開くはずだから
should be opening up
今日も明日もありがとう
Thank you for today and tomorrow
歌い継ぐよ 鮮やかな
I'll keep singing, the vivid...
花を咲かすために
flowers, to make them bloom
ほら 夢満開に してみせるよ
Look, I'll show you I can make our dreams fully bloom
何より強い 命の息吹
A breath of life stronger than anything
運命巡って 奇跡になるから
Fate goes around and becomes a miracle
隣で 綴ってあげる
I'll write it down by your side
小さな 幸せが募る
Small happiness accumulates
みんなへ
To everyone
奇跡のような 君と作るメモリ
Like a miracle, the memories I make with you
はい！というわけで、
Yes! And so,
新曲歌わせていただきましたー！
I've performed my new song!
初めて、こんなドバラードみたいな感じの曲を歌ったので、
It's the first time I've sung such a balladic song,
Elements Gardenさんのね、曲提供していただいた曲なんですけど、
it was provided by Elements Garden,
とってもドキドキしました。ありがとうございます！
and I was very nervous. Thank you!
ありがとう！Thank you, thank you!
Thank you! Thank you, thank you!
さあ、そして、ここからはね、色々なお知らせも、色々喋っていきたいんですが、
Now, from here, I'd like to talk about various announcements,
見てくださいこのステージを！
but look at this stage!
ぬんぬんと、あん肝、そして、わかってたかな？
Nun-nun, Ankimo, and, did you notice?
そらがるすがいたりとか…
There are Sora-Ghouls too...
あとね、こっちにもソファ、こっちにはピアノみたいな感じで、
There's also a sofa over there, and a piano over here,
すごくね、なんか、私らしい感じの、デザインをね、していただきました。
it's a design that feels very "me".
本当にありがとうございます。
Thank you so much.
と、今歌った曲の…にょ。
And, the song I just sang... nyo.
詳細を喋っていきたいと思います。
I'd like to talk about the details.
実はですね、来月2月22日に、EPっていう、
Actually, next month on February 22nd, I'll be releasing an EP,
なんかシングルとアルバムの間みたいな曲が、
which is something between a single and an album,
「Beyond」っていうの、リリースいたします！
called "Beyond"!
2023年2月22日(水) Release New EP 「Beyond」
Releasing Wednesday, February 22, 2023: New EP "Beyond"
先行配信してる「ケ・セラ・ソラ」と、ロジカル・ドロップさんとの提供曲、
It includes "Que Sera Sora" which is currently available, and a song provided by Logical Drop,
さらにハンクラムでのコラボがきっかけで、
plus through the Hancrum collaboration,
草野華余子さん、Elements Gardenさんとコラボした曲4曲を収録しております。
4 songs collaborated with Kayoko Kusano and Elements Garden.
そしてですね、初回限定盤には、昨年11月に開催した、5th Anniversary Live
And, the First Press Limited Edition comes with my 5th Anniversary Live held last November,
「そらと時のミルキーウェイ」昼夜2公演のですね、模様を完全収録した、
containing the full footage of both the day and night performances of "Sora to Toki no Milky Way",
ブルーレイがついております。
a Blu-ray is included.
それが特典なので、ぜひぜひライブをもう一度見たいなって人は、
That's the bonus, so if you want to see the live performance again,
ぜひぜひお手にとってもらえたら嬉しいです。よろしくお願いします。
I'd be happy if you could get it. Thank you.
他にも特典はあるので、詳細は特設サイトをチェックしてね！
There are other bonuses too, so check the special site for details!
そして続いて、今回の記念グッズがあります！
And next, we have the commemorative goods for this occasion!
こちらですね、2分後、22時10分から販売開始となっております。
These will be on sale starting in two minutes, at 22:10.
数量限定もあるので、概要欄チェックしてね！
There are limited quantities, so check the description box!
さっそく内容を見ていきましょう。こちらです！
Let's take a look at the contents. Here it is!
ときのそら 100万人記念 1月29日 22時10分 販売開始
Tokino Sora 1 Million Subscriber Commemoration - Sales start Jan 29, 22:10
1月29日販売開始の...
Starting sales on January 29th...
...100万人記念フルセット！
...the 1 Million Milestone Memorial Full Set!
記念ボイス1種、記念グッズ3種類...
One memorial voice, three types of memorial goods...
そしてですね、数量限定ではあるのですが...
And then, although they are limited in quantity...
直筆サインメッセージ入りポストカードを...
...a postcard with a handwritten signature and message...
書きたいなと思っておりますので...
...is something I'm planning to write...
ぜひぜひよろしくお願いします！
...so please look forward to it!
詳細を見ていきましょう。こちらです！
Let's look at the details. Here they are!
まずは、パブミラーです！
First is the Bub Mirror!
パブミラーはおるだん先生に書いていただきました。
The Bub Mirror was illustrated by Orudan-sensei.
自分の部屋でね、初期の衣装とかね...
In my room, with my early costume...
えーまみちゃんがいたりと、すごく懐かしいものに...
and A-chan being there, it's very nostalgic...
なっているんじゃないでしょうかね。
...don't you think?
そして、まあ家で私はドレスを着てとてもポージング...
And, I'm wearing a dress at home and posing...
しているのでぜひぜひよろしくお願いします。
...so please check it out.
そして、次がこちら。
And next is this.
あんきもタンブラーということで...
The Ankimo Tumbler...
私もですけどね、あの配信の時とかにお水とか...
Like me, when you drink water during a stream...
飲むじゃないですか。テレワークの人でもいいですし...
Right? It's good for people working from home too...
会社に持っていくでもいいですし...
...or you could take it to the office...
シンプルで使いやすいものにしたので...
I made it simple and easy to use...
ぜひぜひみんなもこれに飲み物とかを入れて...
so please, everyone, put your drinks in it...
使ってもらえたら嬉しいなって思います。
...and I'd be happy if you used it.
そして、次はこちら。
And next is this.
マルチケース。こちらはですね...
The Multi-case. This is...
眼鏡ケースになっているんですけど...
...designed as a glasses case...
眼鏡を使わないよって人もいるかなと思ったので...
But I thought some people might not use glasses...
普通に使うとペンケースとしても使えるような...
...so I made it usable as a pen case too...
普段使いができるものを考えました。
...something for everyday use.
眼鏡ケースとして使ってくれてもいいですし...
You can use it as a glasses case...
学校とかあと会社に行く人は...
...or for those who go to school or work...
ぜひペンとかを入れて使っていただけたら...
...please use it to store your pens...
嬉しいなって思います。
...and I'll be happy.
そして、次はこちら。
And next is this.
そうですね、ボイス単体、シチュエーションボイス...
That's right, the voice-only item, a situation voice...
「そらともとホームパーティ」ということで...
"Home Party with Soratomo"...
シチュエーションボイス撮りました。
I've recorded a situation voice.
私、めちゃくちゃ部屋綺麗にしたから...
I've cleaned my room really well...
ぜひぜひホームパーティ遊びに来てほしいな！
...so please come and join the home party!
なんていうようなボイスです。ふふふ。
That's what the voice is like. *chuckles*
最後にこちら。
Lastly, this.
あと20分後に始まります...
Starting in about 20 minutes...
100万人記念フルセット特典購入...
...1 Million Milestone Memorial Full Set Purchase Bonus...
数量限定でこちら直筆サインとメッセージ...
The limited edition includes a handwritten signature and message...
入れさせていただきますので...
I'll be adding those...
よろしくお願いします。ま、もし...
...so please look forward to it. Well, if...
限定間に合わなかったよって人もフルセットで...
...you don't make it for the limited edition, the regular full set...
複製の方もありますのでよろしくお願いします。
...has a printed version too.
数量限定の方は直筆でがっつり書かせていただきます。
I'll be writing the limited edition ones by hand with all my heart.
よろしくお願いします！
Please look forward to it!
そして、最後にファンクラブからお知らせが...
And finally, there are announcements from the fan club...
4つございますので、そちらもぜひ聞いてください。
...four of them, so please listen to them too.
1つ目。なんと、ときのそらオフィシャルファンクラブが...
First. Believe it or not, the Tokino Sora Official Fan Club...
来週で1周年を迎えます！
...will celebrate its 1st anniversary next week!
というわけで、私から会員のみんなに...
And so, I've prepared a present...
プレゼントを用意しました！それがこちらです！
...for all the members! Here it is!
オリジナルアクリルトロフィーを継続特典として...
An Original Acrylic Trophy as a continuous membership bonus...
ご用意しております。スタンダードプランという...
...is what we've prepared. For those on the Standard Plan...
年額会員の方で、ファンクラブを1年以上...
...who are annual members and have been in the fan club for over a year...
366日以上継続していただいた...
...more than 366 days...
実はこのプレゼントがいただける...
...you can receive this gift...
プレゼントするという。えっと、年額じゃないといけない...
...we will present it to you. Well, you have to be an annual member...
というのと、例えば4月に入った人だったら...
...and for example, if someone joined in April...
5月になったらもらえるみたいな感じですかね。
...they'd receive it when May comes around the next year.
詳細はもらえるのがその時か分からないんですけど...
I'm not sure if that's exactly when you'll get it...
詳細はぜひファンクラブの方の記事を見て...
...but for details, please check the article in the fan club...
いただけたら嬉しいなと思います。
...I'd be happy if you did.
そして、お知らせ2つ目は、こちらです。
And the second announcement is this.
ファンクラブ限定バースデーメールというものがあります。
There's a Fan Club Limited Birthday Mail.
会員さんにお誕生日当日に...
On our members' birthdays...
私からお祝いのメールを送ろうかなと思っております。
I'm planning to send a congratulatory email.
みんな楽しみにしててね！
Everyone, please look forward to it!
受信設定をオンにしておくと当日に...
If you turn your reception settings on...
バースデーメールを送らせていただきたいな...
...I'd like to send you a birthday mail on the day.
と思っております。ま、今日とかの人...
That's my plan. Well, for people whose birthday is today...
2月7日までの方、おめでとう！
...or up to February 7th, congratulations!
というわけで、3つ目のお知らせに行きたいと...
And so, moving on to the third announcement...
思います。まずはVTRをご覧ください！
...I'd like to do that. First, please watch this VTR!
TOKINO SORA OFFICIAL FANCLUB
3D STARRING
ロボ子さん
Roboco-san
星街すいせい
Hoshimachi Suisei
さくらみこ
Sakura Miko
AZKi
MC FRIEND-A
and CHAIRMAN IS
ときのそら
TOKINO SORA
Are you ready SORATOMO?
(๑╹◡╹)ぬんぬん
(๑╹◡╹) Nun Nun
SORAPPON GRAND PRIX
はい、イエーイ！
Yes, yay!
というわけで2月5日日曜日19時から...
So, from Sunday, February 5th at 19:00...
「ときのそら決定戦」を生放送で開始に...
...the "Tokino Sora Deciding Match" will be broadcast live...
...いたします！
...we will do it!
えー、このVTR...
Um, this VTR...
そしてその中である そらポン・グランプリっていうね
And within that, there's a project called "Sora-pon Grand Prix,"
企画があるんですけど それのものです
and this is for that.
ゲストに ロボ子さん、すいちゃん、みこち、
Welcoming guests Roboco-san, Suichan, Mikochi,
あずきちの0期生のメンバー そしてMCにえーちゃんをお迎えして
and Azukichi from the 0th gen, with A-chan as the MC.
私に関するいろんな企画をやるということで
We'll be doing various projects related to me,
しかもね 3Dでやりますので
and it will be in 3D,
ぜひ見ていただけたら嬉しいです
so I'd be happy if you'd watch it.
えーそうですね あの
Well, let's see...
YouTubeでもね 途中までは見れるらしいので
It seems you can watch it partway through on YouTube,
そのあとファンクラブまで見に来てくれたら嬉しいなと思います
so I'd be happy if you come to the fan club to see the rest.
最後に4つ目のお知らせです
Finally, the fourth announcement.
なんとファンクラブ限定で とある動画を公開しちゃいます！
I'll be releasing a certain video exclusively for the fan club!
それがこちら！
And here it is!
金沢旅行 2月25日(土)・2月26日(日) ファンクラブにて公開
Kanazawa Trip - Feb 25th (Sat) & Feb 26th (Sun) - To be released on the Fan Club
えー Aちゃんと行ってきた
A video of a trip to Kanazawa
金沢旅行の動画です
I went on with A-chan.
実はね 最近Aちゃんと2人で金沢旅行にね 行ってきました
Actually, A-chan and I went on a trip to Kanazawa together recently.
Aちゃんがね 部屋に起こしに来てくれたりとかね Twitterで上がってたと思うんですけど
A-chan came to my room to wake me up, which I think was on Twitter,
気づいた人はいるのかな？ というわけで なんとですね あの
I wonder if anyone noticed? Anyway, it's actually...
この動画をファンクラブの方で 2月の25日の土曜日、
...we'll be releasing this video in the fan club on Saturday, February 25th,
26日の日曜日の2日間に分けて 限定でですね 公開いたします
and Sunday the 26th, exclusively over these two days.
そしてさらに！
And what's more!
3月4日には 2人でコメンタリーをしながら
On March 4th, we'll also have a live stream
動画をみんなで見る生放送も やりたいなと思っております
where we watch the video together while giving commentary.
プレゼント企画もあるらしいので
There's also going to be a giveaway project,
ね、どんなプレゼントかな？ 気になるね。
so I wonder what the presents are? I'm curious.
ということで詳細はニュースでよろしくお願いします
Check the news for details.
以上 ときのそらオフィシャルファンクラブからの
That's all for the announcements
お知らせでした！みんなホームページチェックしてね！
from the Tokino Sora Official Fan Club! Check the website!
えー 告知盛りだくさんだったんですが
There were so many announcements,
皆さん分かったかな？
did everyone catch them all?
すごい駆け足になっちゃったんですけど
I ended up rushing through them a lot,
えー というわけで今日はね 大切な友達が観に来てくれて
but today, my precious friends came to watch,
そして大切な友達がこうね 配信で一緒に盛り上げてくれて
and my precious friends helped make this stream exciting together,
メッセージもいただけて そしてそらともの皆さんにこんなにたくさん見ていただけて
I got messages, and so many Soratomos are watching,
本当に嬉しいです
I'm really happy.
メッセージをくださった4名の方も 本当にありがとうございました
Thank you so much to the four people who sent messages.
いや、ここまで来れたのも
Really, I believe I was able to come this far
みんなの応援があってこそだと思いますので
only because of everyone's support,
これからもぜひぜひ 応援よろしくお願いいたします
so please continue to support me.
これからも一緒に歩いて行こうね！
Let's keep walking together from now on, too!
100万人を超えても 止まらねぇぞー！
Even after reaching 1 million, I won't stop!
というわけで 今日はこれで終わりにしたいと思います
So, I'd like to end it here for today.
ときのそら100万人への軌跡 いっぱい呟いてね！
Please tweet a lot with #TokinoSoraTrajectoryToOneMillion!
トレンドに乗ってたらいいな、ドキドキ。
I hope it trends, I'm nervous.
今日はありがとうございましたー！うおーい！うおーい！
Thank you for today! Whooo! Whooo!